<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<metadata><NPS_Info><MetaPurp>OnlineData</MetaPurp><MetaPurp>CSDGM</MetaPurp><MetaPurp>NPS</MetaPurp><NPS_Unit><UnitCode>GRCA </UnitCode><UnitType>Park</UnitType></NPS_Unit><DatStore><Category>Boundary </Category><Category>Land Status / Ownership </Category><DataSite>NR-GIS</DataSite><DSteward><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>NPS - Land Resources Division, WASO-FC </cntorg><cntper>Roger Johnson </cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>Chief Cartographer </cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>301 South Howes Street Suite 208 </address><city>Fort Collins </city><state>CO </state><postal>80522 </postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>970-484-6428 </cntvoice><cntfax>970-484-6432 </cntfax><cntemail>roger_m_johnson@nps.gov </cntemail><hours>7:00am-5:30pm Mountain Monday-Thursday </hours></cntinfo></DSteward></DatStore></NPS_Info><idinfo><citation><citeinfo><origin>Department of the Interior (DOI), National Park Service (NPS), Land Resources Division (LRD), Fort Collins Land Resources Program Center </origin><pubdate>20210108  </pubdate><title Sync="FALSE">Grand Canyon National Park Tract and Boundary Data </title><edition>20210108 </edition><pubinfo><pubplace>Fort Collins, CO </pubplace><publish>National Park Service Land Resources Division </publish></pubinfo><onlink>http://nrdata.nps.gov/programs/Lands/grca_tracts.zip </onlink><geoform>vector digital data</geoform></citeinfo></citation><descript><abstract>These ESRI shape files are of National Park Service tract and boundary data that was created by the Land Resources Division. Tracts are numbered and created by the regional cartographic staff at the Land Resources Program Centers and are associated to the Land Status Maps. This data should be used to display properties that NPS owns and properties that NPS may have some type of interest such as scenic easements or right of ways. </abstract><purpose>This data is intended to keep a record of ownership information. Tracts can represent several types of interest like fee and scenic easement, and can be under several types of ownership like NPS owned, private, other federal, state or county. This data set provides accurate and reliable ownership data for park management and acquisition priorities.</purpose><langdata Sync="FALSE">en</langdata></descript><timeperd><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>20100608 </begdate><enddate>20210108 </enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><current>Beginning date is the first recorded conveyance date. Ending date is set to the last day the data set was updated. </current></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>Continually </update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc Sync="TRUE">-113.979901 </westbc><eastbc Sync="TRUE">-111.587066 </eastbc><northbc Sync="TRUE">36.865532 </northbc><southbc Sync="TRUE">35.750278 </southbc></bounding><lboundng><leftbc Sync="TRUE">2483040.622469</leftbc><rightbc Sync="TRUE">2518025.292190</rightbc><bottombc Sync="TRUE">287903.395080</bottombc><topbc Sync="TRUE">313117.765448</topbc></lboundng></spdom><keywords><theme><themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Category</themekt><themekey>Boundaries</themekey><themekey>Planning Cadastre </themekey></theme><theme><themekt>None</themekt><themekey>Boundary</themekey><themekey>Ownership</themekey><themekey>Parcels</themekey><themekey>Tracts</themekey><themekey>LRDCAB </themekey></theme><theme><themekt>National Park Service Theme Category Thesaurus</themekt></theme><place><placekt>None</placekt><placekey>United States </placekey><placekey>National Park Service </placekey><placekey>Grand Canyon National Park </placekey><placekey>Intermountain Region </placekey><placekey>Arizona </placekey></place><place><placekt>National Park System Unit Name Thesaurus</placekt></place><place><placekt>National Park System Unit Code Thesaurus</placekt></place></keywords><accconst>None </accconst><useconst>NPS Director's Order #25 states: "Land status maps will be prepared to identify the ownership of the lands within the authorized boundaries of the park unit. These maps, showing ownership and acreage, are the 'official record' of the acreage of Federal and non-federal lands within the park boundaries. While these maps are the official record of the lands and acreage within the unit's authorized boundaries, they are not of survey quality and not intended to be used for survey purposes." As such this data is intended for use as a tool for GIS analysis. It is in no way intended for engineering or legal purposes. The data accuracy is checked against best available sources which may be dated and vary by location. NPS assumes no liability for use of this data. The boundary polygons LRD creates represent the current legislated boundary of a given NPS unit. NPS does not necessarily have full fee ownership or hold another interest (easement, right of way, etc...) in all parcels contained within this boundary. Equivalently NPS may own or have an interest in parcels outside the legislated boundary of a given unit. In order to obtain complete information about current NPS interests both inside and outside the units legislated boundary, the tracts file created by LRD should be used in conjunction with this boundary file created by LRD.</useconst><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>NPS Land Resources Division, Intermountain Region </cntorg><cntper>Linda Moeder </cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>Cartographer </cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>12795 W. Alameda Pkwy </address><city>Lakewood </city><state>CO </state><postal>80228 </postal><country>USA </country></cntaddr><cntvoice>303-969-2621 </cntvoice><cntfax>303-969-2599 </cntfax><cntemail>linda_moeder@nps.gov </cntemail><hours>7:00am - 3:30pm Mountain (Monday-Friday) </hours></cntinfo></ptcontac><citeinfo>Microsoft Windows XP - Service Pack 2, Autodesk Land Desktop 2006 Project (DWG format)  </citeinfo><natvform Sync="FALSE">Shapefile</natvform></idinfo><dataqual><attracc><attraccr>The Tract_id, and Alpha data fields are provided by regional cartographic offices. The Date_Edit data field is added when the regional office submits the data to the Lands WASO Fort Collins office for inclusion in the national data set. All remaining tract attributes are updated from LRD's Master Deed Listing (MDL) nightly. By default the Status and Estate fields are included shape file dbf. All other MDL fields covered under the FOIA can be added to the tract dbf upon request.</attraccr></attracc><logic>Link and node polygon topology is created using AutoDesk Land Desktop 2006. The data is then exported to ESRI shape file format and reprojected from it's native Autodesk coordinate system to NAD83 generic latitude and longitude, LL83. </logic><complete>Information contained in LRD's land ownership databases is updated nightly however tract polygons are posted to the NPS Data Store on a monthly basis. Users can ensure parcel polygons have up to date ownership attribution after the publication date by contacting your regional LRD office or downloading the Current_Tract_Ownership_Data file located on the NPS Data Store (http://science.nature.nps.gov/nrdata/) in a dBase format. Please contact the data originator with any suggested corrections and updates. LRD's boundary polygons represent the current legislated boundary of a given NPS unit. NPS does not necessarily have full fee ownership or hold another interest (easement, right of way, etc...) in all parcels contained within this boundary. Equivalently NPS may own or have an interest in parcels outside the legislated boundary of a given unit. In order to obtain complete information about current NPS interests both inside and outside the units legislated boundary, LRD's tracts files should also be downloaded and used in conjunction with LRD's boundary files. BLM GCDB data was used in order to complete the majority of the boundary and tracts for GRCA. This was done by importing GCDB files for each township and range that encompass the park. Where no GCDB data existed for Canyon Rim portions of the boundary, USGS SDTS hypsography files were processed in ArcMap and converted to converages, then converted to shapefiles. The boundary along the southern bank of the Colorado River was completed the same way by using USGS hydrography data. Where GCDB data did exist that coincided with the boundary, linework was copied from the PLSS layer to the tract or boundary layer. In order to map the interior and exterior tracts, deeds, legal descriptions, USGS SDTS transportation data, Arizona State Land Department, Arizona Land Resources Information System data was used. Some tract boundaries were not as definitive. The process for mapping these tracts is as follows: On-screen digitized east bank of Colorado river in T30N-R14W, SECTION 10 (NW1/4, NW1/4), Section 3 (SW ¼, SW1/4). Due to incomplete hydro data. On-screen digitized east bank of Colorado river in T31N-R14W, SECTION 29 (NW1/4, SW1/4 AND NW1/4, SE1/4), Section 30 (NE1/4, SE1/4 AND NE1/4, SW1/4 AND NW1/4, SW1/4 AND NW1/4, SE1/4 ). Due to incomplete hydro data. On-screen digitized east bank of Colorado river in T31N-R15W, SECTION 26 (NE1/4, NE1/4 AND NE1/4, NW1/4) Due to incomplete hydro data. Approximately 4066 feet north of the corner of T40N R7E DIGITIZED THE EAST RIM OF THE CANYON due to lack of hypsography for the Lee’s Ferry quadrangle. Mojave parcels imported, and transformed around points X = 1020605.23 Y = 13158684.38 and X = 1019313.87, Y = 13160032.84 Eastern boundary of tract 105-01 digitized from segment map. Tract 104-02 is 200ft right of way according to miscellaneous map grca11311976-001.pdf found here: http://landsnet.nps.gov/tractsnet/documents/grca/Miscellaneous_Maps/grca11311976-001.pdf. For further verification, the tract was accessed on the Coconino County Parcel Viewer, printed off to a scale of 1:600 (1:50ft) and then measured. Eastern boundary of tract 107-22 digitized from segment map. The Arizona state land ownership portion of the land coverage is updated along with the surface parcels coverage. All changes to the surface parcels are performed by the CAD department. They are then given to the GIS department in a DXF file on a township by township basis. Through a series of AMLs and editing procedures, the changes in the DXF file are incorporated into the surface parcels and land coverages. Changes in federal agencies are done primarily through the Bureau of Land Management (BLM) using a customized AML based application of ArcInfo. BLM incorporates its changes as well as others such as the Forest Service, Bureau of Reclamation, Fish &amp; Wildlife Service, National Park Service, etc. BLM and State of Arizona status is updated approximately every six months, other agencies are updated on an irregular basis. Data is obtained from both the Bureau of Land Management and Bureau of Indian Affairs on a somewhat regular basis and incorporated into the land coverage as necessary. DOQQs production procedures, instrumentation, hardware and software used in the collection of standard USGS DOQ's vary depending on systems used at the contract, cooperator or USGS production sites. The majority of DOQ datasets are acquired through government contract. The process step describes, in general, the process used in the production of USGS DOQ data sets. The rectification process requires, as input, a user parameter file to the rectification process, a digital elevation model gridded to specified bounds, projection, zone, datum and X-Y units, a scanned image file covering the same area as the DEM, ground X-Y-Z point values and their conjugate photo coordinates in the camera coordinate system, and measurements of the fiducial in the digitized image. The camera calibration report provides the length of the camera and the distances in millimeters from the optical center to the camera's 8 fiducial marks. These marks define the field of reference for spatial measurements made from the photograph. Ground control points acquired from ground surveys or developed in aerotriangulation, are third order class 1 or better, and meet National Map Accuracy Standard (NMAS) for 1:12,000-scale. Ground control points are in the Universal Transverse Mercator or the State Plane Coordinate System on NAD83. Horizontal and vertical residuals of aerotriangulated tie-points are equal to or less than 2.5 meters. Standard aerotriangulation passpoint configuration consists of 9 ground control points, one near each corner, one at the center near each side and 1 near the center of the photograph, are used. The conjugate positions of the ground control points on the photograph are measured and recorded in camera coordinates. The raster image file is created by scanning an aerial photograph film diapositive with a precision image scanner. An aperture of approximately 25 to 32 microns is used, with an aperture no greater than 32 microns permitted. Digital Line Graphs were digitized from the USGS source quadrangle, by either the National Mapping Division, one of their cooperators, or one of their contractors. The digital data were produced by one of the following methods: - scanning a stable-based copy of the graphic materials. The scanning process captured the digital data at a scanning resolution of at least 0.001 inches. Once tract and boundary data was complete, topology was successfully built and then exported. The data was georeferenced using UTM coordinate system, NAD 83, Zone 12. Once the shapefiles were exported, they were converted to LL83. USGS DLG 7.5’ Hypsography: USGS DLG Hypsography lines were traced to define the Grand Canyon Rim, beginning at well-defined clearly discernible rim locations from recognized reference data, including USGS 1:24K DRG topographic maps, USGS nominal 10-meter Digital Elevation Model data (derived slope model), USDA one-meter NAIP Imagery (2010 and 2007). Single Hypsographic lines were traced along the rim. At points where reference data visually indicate that the individual hypsographic contour line diverges from the canyon rim, tracing was offset to the next nearest hypsographic line that closest follows the canyon rim. In locations were the rim is not clearly shown on reference data, hypsographic contour lines from well-established locations were continued, where possible, so long as they generally followed GRCA Segment maps or other reference data. For side canyons, hypsographic rim contours were followed into side canyons, so long as they did not diverge significantly from GRCA Segment maps or other reference data. If this resulted in following a contour far beyond what was indicated on the Segment maps or other reference data, the digitized lines were stepped down/up along visible geographic features, in particular secondary side canyons or NHD Streamline features. Where GRCA Segment maps or Solicitor opinions indicate that the Boundary is offset from the canyon rim (this occurs on the South Rim, where the boundary is defined as “…one-quarter mile from the canyon rim…”), the defined canyon rim was buffered by the legislated distance. USGS DLG 7.5’ Boundary: Where reference data indicate that the GRCA Boundary does not follow the canyon rim, USGS DLG Boundary data were used wherever they have been defined. After careful inspection, this data is considered much truer to the Legislated Boundary than USBLM GCDB data of the same features. USGS NHD Area: USGS NHD Area data, downloaded in January 2011 from USGS, was used as the reference data where the GRCA Boundary is defined as the Colorado River bank. This occurs along the border with the Hualapai Reservation and along the GLCA Boundary. The data used is more recent than what had been previously used. USGS NHD Flowline: USGS NHD Flowline data was used where the GRCA Boundary is defined by a stream course. This occurs in only one location, along Indian Hollow and Jumpup Canyons. The original legislation defining the park boundary in T32N R15W references an “unsurveyed township” meaning the United States government had not completed a rectangular survey of the area being defined at the time of legislation. The congressional action assumed the sections would be surveyed in a “typical” manner, meaning 36 regular sections of approximately 640 acres each, one mile per section side. When the survey was completed, an irregular township (32½ N) was added to the north of T32N. The boundary identified in the legislation contains a call to section 25 (unsurveyed). The current location of section 25 is now south of the intended location by about 3,600 feet (due to the irregular township). Because the intended location of the legislated boundary is based on an assumed regular township, the boundary does not match the section calls in the legislation. Historical boundary maps of GRCA confirm this boundary location. Any Navajo Lands within the boundary depicted on this map are a part of the legislated boundary, and may be different than the administrative boundary. Also, notes will appear on the Land Status Maps in these areas, in order to avert confusion with regards to any and all Navajo Lands that fall within the legislated boundary.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>For the USGS DLG Data Horizontal positional accuracy is based upon the use of USGS source quadrangles which are compiled to meet National Map Accuracy Standards (NMAS). NMAS horizontal accuracy requires that at least 90 percent of points tested are within 0.02 inches of the true position. The digital data are estimated to contain a horizontal positional error of less than or equal to 0.003 inches standard error in the two component directions relative to the source quadrangle. Comparison to the graphic source is used as control to assess digital positional accuracy. For the BLM GCDB Data the majority of coordinates in this dataset fall within +/- 40 feet spatial accuracy (the general rule of thumb to be called 1:24,000-scale data). For the DOQQs the horizontal positional accuracy and the assurance of that accuracy depend, in part, on the accuracy of the data inputs to the rectification process. These inputs consist of the digital elevation model (DEM),aerotriangulation control and methods, the photo source camera calibration, scanner calibration, and aerial photographs that meet National Aerial Photography Program (NAPP) standards. The vertical accuracy of the verified USGS format DEM is equivalent to or better than a USGS level 1 or 2 DEM, with a root mean square error (RMSE) of no greater than 7.0 meters. Field control is acquired by third order class 1 or better survey methods sufficiently spaced to meet National Map Accuracy Staandards (NMAS) for 1:12,000-scale products. Aerial cameras have current certification from the USGS, National Mapping Division, Optical Science Laboratory. Test calibration scans are performed on all source photography scanners. Horizontal positional accuracy is determined by the Orthophoto Accuracy (ORACC) software program for DOQ data produced by the National Mapping Division. The program determines the accuracy by finding the line and sample coordinates of the passpoints in the DOQ and fitting these to their ground coordinates to develop a root mean square error (RMSE). From 4 to 9 points are checked. As a further accuracy test, the image line and sample coordinates of the DEM corners are transformed and compared with the actual X,Y DEM corner values to determine if they are within the RMSE. Smaller scale maps have a larger level of inaccuracy. It is assumed that the boundary and tract information meets National Map Accuracy Standards and should be considered no better than the listed sources.</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>None</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>National Park Service - Land Resources Division </origin><pubdate>20210108 </pubdate><title>Legal Descriptions </title><edition>N/A </edition><geoform>document - legal description </geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Fort Collins </pubplace><publish>Land Resources Division </publish></pubinfo><othercit>MANDATORY IF APPLICABLE </othercit></citeinfo></srccite><srcscale>1 </srcscale><typesrc>Paper </typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>19280601 </begdate><enddate>20040806 </enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><srccurr>Beginning Date represents first conveyed date. Ending date is when the data was last updated. </srccurr></srctime><srccitea>Legal Descriptions </srccitea><srccontr>tract and boundary geometry, Tract_id, Alpha </srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>National Park Service - Land Resources Division </origin><pubdate>20210108 </pubdate><title>Deeds </title><edition>N/A </edition><geoform>document - deed </geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Fort Collins </pubplace><publish>Land Resources Division </publish></pubinfo><othercit>MANDATORY IF APPLICABLE </othercit></citeinfo></srccite><srcscale>1 </srcscale><typesrc>Paper </typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>19280601 </begdate><enddate>20210108  </enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><srccurr>Beginning Date represents first conveyed date. Ending date is when the data was last updated. </srccurr></srctime><srccitea>deeds </srccitea><srccontr>tract and boundary geometry, Tract_id, Alpha </srccontr></srcinfo><srcinfo><srccite><citeinfo><origin>National Park Service - Land Resources Division </origin><pubdate>20210108 </pubdate><title>Segment Maps </title><edition>N/A </edition><geoform>map - segment map </geoform><pubinfo><pubplace>Fort Collins </pubplace><publish>Land Resources Division </publish></pubinfo><othercit>MANDATORY IF APPLICABLE </othercit></citeinfo></srccite><srcscale>1:3600-1:63360 </srcscale><typesrc>Mylar </typesrc><srctime><timeinfo><rngdates><begdate>197507 </begdate><enddate>197507  </enddate></rngdates></timeinfo><srccurr>Beginning Date represents first conveyed date. Ending date is when the data was last updated. </srccurr></srctime><srccitea>segment maps </srccitea><srccontr>tract and boundary geometry, Tract_id, Alpha </srccontr></srcinfo><procstep><procdesc>Updated 01/08/2021: Adjusted the legislated boundary to include tract 109-01. Originally Published 07/16/2018: The Autodesk line work is imported, edited, attributed, approved, and a link and node topology is developed both for the tract and boundary data layers according to the procedures described in the Land Acquisition Procedures Manual Chapter 5. The entire unit is created in a geographically contiguous model space and separate layouts representing each individual segment map are created. The tract and boundary data is then reprojected to North American Datum 1983 generic latitude &amp; longitude and exported from Autodesk to an ArcView shape file format in a single step. BLM GCDB data was used in order to complete the majority of the boundary and tracts for GRCA. This was done by importing GCDB files for each township and range that encompass the park. Where no GCDB data existed for Canyon Rim portions of the boundary, USGS SDTS hypsography files were processed in ArcMap and converted to converages, then converted to shapefiles. The boundary along the southern bank of the Colorado River was completed the same way by using USGS hydrography data. Where GCDB data did exist that coincided with the boundary, linework was copied from the PLSS layer to the tract or boundary layer. In order to map the interior and exterior tracts, deeds, legal descriptions, USGS SDTS transportation data, Arizona State Land Department, Arizona Land Resources Information System data was used. Some tract boundaries were not as definitive. The process for mapping these tracts is as follows: On-screen digitized east bank of Colorado river in T30N-R14W, SECTION 10 (NW1/4, NW1/4), Section 3 (SW ¼, SW1/4). Due to incomplete hydro data. On-screen digitized east bank of Colorado river in T31N-R14W, SECTION 29 (NW1/4, SW1/4 AND NW1/4, SE1/4), Section 30 (NE1/4, SE1/4 AND NE1/4, SW1/4 AND NW1/4, SW1/4 AND NW1/4, SE1/4 ). Due to incomplete hydro data. On-screen digitized east bank of Colorado river in T31N-R15W, SECTION 26 (NE1/4, NE1/4 AND NE1/4, NW1/4) Due to incomplete hydro data. Approximately 4066 feet north of the corner of T40N R7E DIGITIZED THE EAST RIM OF THE CANYON due to lack of hypsography for the Lee’s Ferry quadrangle. Mojave parcels imported, and transformed around points X = 1020605.23 Y = 13158684.38 and X = 1019313.87, Y = 13160032.84 Eastern boundary of tract 105-01 digitized from segment map. Tract 104-02 is 200ft right of way according to miscellaneous map grca11311976-001.pdf found here: http://landsnet.nps.gov/tractsnet/documents/grca/Miscellaneous_Maps/grca11311976-001.pdf. For further verification, the tract was accessed on the Coconino County Parcel Viewer, printed off to a scale of 1:600 (1:50ft) and then measured. Eastern boundary of tract 107-22 digitized from segment map. The Arizona state land ownership portion of the land coverage is updated along with the surface parcels coverage. All changes to the surface parcels are performed by the CAD department. They are then given to the GIS department in a DXF file on a township by township basis. Through a series of AMLs and editing procedures, the changes in the DXF file are incorporated into the surface parcels and land coverages. Changes in federal agencies are done primarily through the Bureau of Land Management (BLM) using a customized AML based application of ArcInfo. BLM incorporates its changes as well as others such as the Forest Service, Bureau of Reclamation, Fish &amp; Wildlife Service, National Park Service, etc. BLM and State of Arizona status is updated approximately every six months, other agencies are updated on an irregular basis. Data is obtained from both the Bureau of Land Management and Bureau of Indian Affairs on a somewhat regular basis and incorporated into the land coverage as necessary. DOQQs production procedures, instrumentation, hardware and software used in the collection of standard USGS DOQ's vary depending on systems used at the contract, cooperator or USGS production sites. The majority of DOQ datasets are acquired through government contract. The process step describes, in general, the process used in the production of USGS DOQ data sets. The rectification process requires, as input, a user parameter file to the rectification process, a digital elevation model gridded to specified bounds, projection, zone, datum and X-Y units, a scanned image file covering the same area as the DEM, ground X-Y-Z point values and their conjugate photo coordinates in the camera coordinate system, and measurements of the fiducial in the digitized image. The camera calibration report provides the length of the camera and the distances in millimeters from the optical center to the camera's 8 fiducial marks. These marks define the field of reference for spatial measurements made from the photograph. Ground control points acquired from ground surveys or developed in aerotriangulation, are third order class 1 or better, and meet National Map Accuracy Standard (NMAS) for 1:12,000-scale. Ground control points are in the Universal Transverse Mercator or the State Plane Coordinate System on NAD83. Horizontal and vertical residuals of aerotriangulated tie-points are equal to or less than 2.5 meters. Standard aerotriangulation passpoint configuration consists of 9 ground control points, one near each corner, one at the center near each side and 1 near the center of the photograph, are used. The conjugate positions of the ground control points on the photograph are measured and recorded in camera coordinates. The raster image file is created by scanning an aerial photograph film diapositive with a precision image scanner. An aperture of approximately 25 to 32 microns is used, with an aperture no greater than 32 microns permitted. Digital Line Graphs were digitized from the USGS source quadrangle, by either the National Mapping Division, one of their cooperators, or one of their contractors. The digital data were produced by one of the following methods: - scanning a stable-based copy of the graphic materials. The scanning process captured the digital data at a scanning resolution of at least 0.001 inches. Once tract and boundary data was complete, topology was successfully built and then exported. The data was georeferenced using UTM coordinate system, NAD 83, Zone 12. Once the shapefiles were exported, they were converted to LL83. USGS DLG 7.5’ Hypsography: USGS DLG Hypsography lines were traced to define the Grand Canyon Rim, beginning at well-defined clearly discernible rim locations from recognized reference data, including USGS 1:24K DRG topographic maps, USGS nominal 10-meter Digital Elevation Model data (derived slope model), USDA one-meter NAIP Imagery (2010 and 2007). Single Hypsographic lines were traced along the rim. At points where reference data visually indicate that the individual hypsographic contour line diverges from the canyon rim, tracing was offset to the next nearest hypsographic line that closest follows the canyon rim. In locations were the rim is not clearly shown on reference data, hypsographic contour lines from well-established locations were continued, where possible, so long as they generally followed GRCA Segment maps or other reference data. For side canyons, hypsographic rim contours were followed into side canyons, so long as they did not diverge significantly from GRCA Segment maps or other reference data. If this resulted in following a contour far beyond what was indicated on the Segment maps or other reference data, the digitized lines were stepped down/up along visible geographic features, in particular secondary side canyons or NHD Streamline features. Where GRCA Segment maps or Solicitor opinions indicate that the Boundary is offset from the canyon rim (this occurs on the South Rim, where the boundary is defined as “…one-quarter mile from the canyon rim…”), the defined canyon rim was buffered by the legislated distance. USGS DLG 7.5’ Boundary: Where reference data indicate that the GRCA Boundary does not follow the canyon rim, USGS DLG Boundary data were used wherever they have been defined. After careful inspection, this data is considered much truer to the Legislated Boundary than USBLM GCDB data of the same features. USGS NHD Area: USGS NHD Area data, downloaded in January 2011 from USGS, was used as the reference data where the GRCA Boundary is defined as the Colorado River bank. This occurs along the border with the Hualapai Reservation and along the GLCA Boundary. The data used is more recent than what had been previously used. USGS NHD Flowline: USGS NHD Flowline data was used where the GRCA Boundary is defined by a stream course. This occurs in only one location, along Indian Hollow and Jumpup Canyons. The original legislation defining the park boundary in T32N R15W references an “unsurveyed township” meaning the United States government had not completed a rectangular survey of the area being defined at the time of legislation. The congressional action assumed the sections would be surveyed in a “typical” manner, meaning 36 regular sections of approximately 640 acres each, one mile per section side. When the survey was completed, an irregular township (32½ N) was added to the north of T32N. The boundary identified in the legislation contains a call to section 25 (unsurveyed). The current location of section 25 is now south of the intended location by about 3,600 feet (due to the irregular township). Because the intended location of the legislated boundary is based on an assumed regular township, the boundary does not match the section calls in the legislation. Historical boundary maps of GRCA confirm this boundary location. Please reference map number 133/20,021-B for the legislated boundary. Any Navajo Lands within the boundary depicted on this map are a part of the legislated boundary, and may be different than the administrative boundary. Also, notes will appear on the Land Status Maps in these areas, in order to avert confusion with regards to any and all Navajo Lands that fall within the legislated boundary.</procdesc><srcused>Segment Maps 101-113 found here: http://landsnet.nps.gov/tractsnet/documents/grca/Segment_Maps/ </srcused><srcused>Deeds 1-128 found here: http://landsnet.nps.gov/tractsnet/documents/grca/Deeds/ </srcused><srcused>Miscellaneous Maps found here: http://landsnet.nps.gov/tractsnet/documents/grca/Miscellaneous_Maps/ </srcused><srcused>Legislative summary found here: http://landsnet.nps.gov/tractsnet/documents/grca/Legislation/grca_summary.pdf </srcused><srcused>Change orders found here: http://landsnet.nps.gov/tractsnet/documents/grca/Change_Orders/ </srcused><srcused>BLM GCDB Data </srcused><srcused>Mohave and Coconino Counties Digital Orthophoto mosaics </srcused><srcused>1:24k USGS DLG data for Hypsography, Hydrography, and Transportation </srcused><srcused>Arizona Surface Management Parcel Data from the Arizona State Land Department, Arizona Land Resources Information System </srcused><srcused>USGS 24K Quads </srcused><procdate>20100608 -20210108 </procdate><proccont><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Linda Moeder </cntper><cntorg>NPS Land Resources Division, Intermountain Region </cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Cartographer </cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>12795 W. Alameda Pkwy </address><city>Lakewood </city><state>CO </state><postal>80228 </postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>303-969-2621 </cntvoice><cntfax>303-969-2599 </cntfax><cntemail>linda_moeder@nps.gov </cntemail><hours>7:00am - 3:30pm Mountain (Monday-Friday) </hours></cntinfo></proccont></procstep></lineage></dataqual><spref><horizsys>
		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 

		- 
<geograph><latres>0.000002</latres><longres>0.000002</longres><geogunit>Decimal degrees</geogunit></geograph><geodetic><horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn><ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips><semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis><denflat>298.257222</denflat></geodetic></horizsys></spref><eainfo><detailed><enttyp><enttypl Sync="FALSE">grca_tracts.dbf </enttypl><enttypd>Shapefile Attribute Table </enttypd><enttypds>None </enttypds><enttypt Sync="FALSE">Feature Class</enttypt><enttypc Sync="FALSE">226</enttypc></enttyp><attr><attrlabl Sync="FALSE">Alpha </attrlabl><attrdef Sync="FALSE">Provides the unit identification code. </attrdef><attrdefs Sync="FALSE">"Land Acquisition Procedures (LAPS)", revised 2009. </attrdefs><attrdomv><udom Sync="FALSE">Attributes were created according to the National Park Service, Washington Land Resources Division, Land Acquisition Procedures (LAPS) revised 2005. </udom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="FALSE">Alpha </attalias><attrtype Sync="FALSE">String </attrtype><attwidth Sync="FALSE">4 </attwidth><atprecis Sync="FALSE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="FALSE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="FALSE">Tract_id </attrlabl><attalias Sync="FALSE">Tract_Id </attalias><attrtype Sync="FALSE">String </attrtype><attwidth Sync="FALSE">256 </attwidth><atprecis Sync="FALSE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="FALSE">0</attscale><attrdef Sync="FALSE">Provides the tract identification number. </attrdef><attrdefs Sync="FALSE">"Land Acquisition Procedures (LAPS)", revised 2009. </attrdefs><attrdomv><udom Sync="FALSE">Attributes were created according to the National Park Service, Washington Land Resources Division, Land Acquisition Procedures (LAPS) revised 2009. </udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="FALSE">Status </attrlabl><attrdef Sync="FALSE">Defines if an interest is a parcel is NPS owned, held by another Federal agency or a non-Federal party. </attrdef><attrdefs Sync="FALSE">"Land Acquisition Procedures (LAPS)", revised 2009. </attrdefs><attrdomv><udom Sync="FALSE">Attributes were created according to the National Park Service, Washington Land Resources Division, Land Acquisition Procedures (LAPS) revised 2009. </udom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="FALSE">Status </attalias><attrtype Sync="FALSE">String </attrtype><attwidth Sync="FALSE">16 </attwidth><atprecis Sync="FALSE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="FALSE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="FALSE">Estate </attrlabl><attrdef Sync="FALSE">Expresses the degree, nature, quality, or extent of an interest NPS has acquired. </attrdef><attrdefs Sync="FALSE">"Land Acquisition Procedures (LAPS)", revised 2009. </attrdefs><attrdomv><udom Sync="FALSE">Attributes were created according to the National Park Service, Washington Land Resources Division, Land Acquisition Procedures (LAPS) revised 2009. </udom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="FALSE">Estate </attalias><attrtype Sync="FALSE">String </attrtype><attwidth Sync="FALSE">16 </attwidth><atprecis Sync="FALSE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="FALSE">0</attscale></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="FALSE">Areatract </attrlabl><attrdef Sync="FALSE">A field used to relate each parcel to the Current_Tract_Ownership_Data.dbf file located on the NPS Data Store. </attrdef><attrdefs Sync="FALSE">"Land Acquisition Procedures (LAPS)", revised 2009. </attrdefs><attrdomv><udom Sync="FALSE">Attributes were created according to the National Park Service, Washington Land Resources Division, Land Acquisition Procedures (LAPS) revised 2009. </udom></attrdomv><attalias Sync="FALSE">Areatract </attalias><attrtype Sync="FALSE">String </attrtype><attwidth Sync="FALSE">16 </attwidth><atprecis Sync="FALSE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="FALSE">0</attscale></attr></detailed><overview><eaover>Attributes were created according to the National Park Service, Land Resources Division, Land Acquisition Procedures (LAPS).</eaover><eadetcit>"Land Acquisition Procedures (LAPS)", Mapping Standards - Chapter 5, revised 2009. </eadetcit></overview></eainfo><distinfo><distrib><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>NPS - Land Resources Division, WASO-FC </cntorg><cntper>Roger Johnson </cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>Chief Cartographer </cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>301 South Howes Street Suite 208 </address><city>Fort Collins </city><state>CO </state><postal>80522 </postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>970-484-6428 </cntvoice><cntfax>970-484-6432 </cntfax><cntemail>roger_m_johnson@nps.gov </cntemail><hours>7:00am-5:30pm Mountain Monday-Thursday </hours></cntinfo></distrib><distliab>Property ownership data is compiled from deeds, plats, surveys, and other source data. These are not engineering quality drawings and should be used for administrative purposes only. The National Park Service shall not be held liable for improper or incorrect use of the data described and/or contained herein. These data and related graphics are not legal documents and are not intended to be used as such. The information contained in these data is dynamic and may change over time. The data are not better than the original sources from which they were derived. It is the responsibility of the data user to use the data appropriately and consistent within the limitations of geospatial data in general and these data in particular. The related graphics are intended to aid the data user in acquiring relevant data; it is not appropriate to use the related graphics as data. The National Park Service gives no warranty, expressed or implied, as to the accuracy, reliability, or completeness of these data. It is strongly recommended that these data are directly acquired from an NPS server and not indirectly through other sources which may have changed the data in some way. Although these data have been processed successfully on a computer system at the National Park Service, no warranty expressed or implied is made regarding the utility of the data on another system or for general or scientific purposes, nor shall the act of distribution constitute any such warranty. This disclaimer applies both to individual use of the data and aggregate use with other data.</distliab><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><formname>ESRI Shapefile </formname></digtinfo><digtopt><onlinopt><computer><networka><networkr>http://nrdata.nps.gov/programs/Lands/grca_tracts.zip </networkr></networka></computer></onlinopt></digtopt></digform><fees>None </fees></stdorder><resdesc>grca.shp and grca_boundary.shp </resdesc><custom>
To get a hard copy plot, contact Land Resources Program
Center for replacement costs and turnaround times.
</custom></distinfo><metainfo><metd Sync="FALSE">20210108 </metd><metc><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntorg>NPS Land Resources Division, Intermountain Region </cntorg><cntper>Linda Moeder </cntper></cntorgp><cntpos>Cartographer </cntpos><cntaddr><addrtype>Mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>12795 W. Alameda Pkwy </address><city>Lakewood  </city><state>CO </state><postal>80228 </postal><country>USA</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>303-969-2621 </cntvoice><cntfax>303-969-2599 </cntfax><cntemail>linda_moeder@nps.gov </cntemail><hours>7:00am - 3:30pm Mountain (Monday-Friday) </hours></cntinfo></metc><metstdn Sync="FALSE">FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata </metstdn><metstdv Sync="FALSE">FGDC-STD-001-1998 </metstdv><metextns><onlink Sync="FALSE">http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink><metprof Sync="FALSE">ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof></metextns><metextns><onlink Sync="FALSE">http://nrdata.nps.gov/profiles/NPS_Profile.xml</onlink><metprof Sync="FALSE">NPS Metadata Profile</metprof></metextns><langmeta Sync="FALSE">en</langmeta><mettc Sync="FALSE">local time</mettc></metainfo></metadata>
